<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://arafatikram.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://arafatikram.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-11T13:59:58+00:00</updated><id>https://arafatikram.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Arafat Ibne Ikram, Bangladeshi Renewable Energy and Sustainable Development Researcher, notable research are microgrid optimization, power to gas - hydrogen as energy storage, ANFIS MPPT </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Optimizing Smart Home Energy Consumption Strategies</title><link href="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/load-scheduling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimizing Smart Home Energy Consumption Strategies"/><published>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/load-scheduling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/load-scheduling/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="foundation">Foundation</h2> <p>In an era of rising fuel prices and growing environmental concerns, optimizing energy consumption in households has become more critical than ever. A recent research paper titled “Optimizing Energy Consumption in Smart Homes: Load Scheduling Approaches” by A. I. Ikram and colleagues presents an innovative solution to this challenge. The study explores how smart home energy management systems (SHEMS) can reduce electricity costs and minimize peak-to-average energy consumption ratios while maintaining user comfort.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="challenges">Challenges</h2> <p>Traditional energy grids rely heavily on fossil fuels, contributing to carbon emissions and environmental degradation. With the increasing adoption of renewable energy sources (RES) like solar panels, managing energy consumption efficiently has become complex. The study addresses this by focusing on:</p> <ul> <li>Reducing electricity costs for homeowners.</li> <li>Balancing energy demand to avoid peak-hour overloads.</li> <li>Integrating renewable energy sources like solar power with battery storage.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="proposed-solution">Proposed Solution</h2> <p>The researchers developed a smart home model equipped with:</p> <ul> <li>Rooftop solar panels for renewable energy generation.</li> <li>Battery storage to store excess solar energy.</li> <li>Shiftable and non-shiftable loads to categorize household appliances based on their flexibility in usage time.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Diagram-load-scheduling-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/Diagram-load-scheduling-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/Diagram-load-scheduling-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Diagram-load-scheduling.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> System Diagram. </div> <hr/> <p>Key Components:</p> <h3 id="solar-panel-modeling">Solar Panel Modeling</h3> <ul> <li>The study used mathematical models to estimate solar energy generation based on sunlight availability.</li> <li>Equations accounted for solar radiation, temperature, and panel efficiency to predict hourly energy output.</li> </ul> <h3 id="battery-storage-system">Battery Storage System</h3> <ul> <li>Excess solar energy was stored in batteries for use during non-generating hours (e.g., nighttime).</li> <li>The state of charge (SOC) of the battery was monitored to ensure optimal energy usage.</li> </ul> <h3 id="load-classification">Load Classification</h3> <ul> <li>Shiftable Loads: Appliances like washing machines, water heaters, and microwaves, whose usage times can be adjusted.</li> <li>Non-Shiftable Loads: Essential appliances like refrigerators and lights that must operate continuously.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="optimization-techniques">Optimization Techniques</h2> <p>The study employed two meta-heuristic algorithms to schedule shiftable loads efficiently:</p> <h3 id="particle-swarm-optimization-pso">Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO)</h3> <ul> <li>Inspired by the social behavior of birds, PSO iteratively adjusts the time of use (TOU) for appliances to minimize costs.</li> <li>It quickly converges to optimal solutions by balancing individual and collective best positions.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/PSO-load-scheduling-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/PSO-load-scheduling-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/PSO-load-scheduling-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/PSO-load-scheduling.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> System Diagram. </div> <h3 id="real-coded-genetic-algorithm-rcga">Real-Coded Genetic Algorithm (RCGA)</h3> <ul> <li>A variation of genetic algorithms using real-valued vectors to represent appliance schedules.</li> <li>It uses crossover and mutation to explore optimal TOU configurations, ensuring diversity in solutions.</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/GA-load-scheduling-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/GA-load-scheduling-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/GA-load-scheduling-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/GA-load-scheduling.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> System Diagram. </div> <hr/> <h2 id="results-and-outcomes">Results and Outcomes</h2> <p>The optimization strategies yielded impressive results:</p> <ul> <li>Reduced Electricity Costs: Daily costs dropped from 507.12 BDT (before optimization) to 484.33 BDT, a 4.5% reduction.</li> <li>Lower Peak Demand: Load curves showed a more balanced energy distribution, avoiding spikes during peak hours.</li> <li>User Comfort Maintained: Appliances operated at optimal times without disrupting daily routines.</li> </ul> <p>Key Findings:</p> <ul> <li>PSO vs. RCGA: Both algorithms achieved similar cost reductions, but RCGA produced a more symmetrical load curve, avoiding excessive peak demands.</li> <li>Seasonal Variations: The model was tested for both summer and winter, showing consistent performance across different energy consumption patterns.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="future-directions">Future Directions</h2> <p>The study opens doors for further advancements:</p> <ul> <li>Hybrid Energy Systems: Integrating wind turbines or diesel generators alongside solar panels.</li> <li>Real-Time Pricing Models: Adapting to dynamic electricity tariffs for even greater savings.</li> <li>vAdvanced Algorithms: Exploring other optimization techniques like deep reinforcement learning for smarter scheduling.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>This research demonstrates how smart home energy management systems can significantly cut costs and improve efficiency. By leveraging renewable energy and intelligent load scheduling, households can contribute to a greener future while enjoying economic benefits.</p> <p>For homeowners, utilities, and policymakers, these findings highlight the potential of SHEMS in revolutionizing energy consumption. As technology evolves, smarter and more adaptive systems will further enhance these benefits, paving the way for sustainable living.</p> <hr/> <p>Interested in the full paper? Check out the original research here (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1049/pel2.12663">link to the paper</a>).</p>]]></content><author><name>Arafat Ibne Ikram</name></author><category term="SmartHome,"/><category term="Optimization,"/><category term="LoadScheduling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Optimizing Energy Consumption in Smart Homes A Breakthrough in Load Scheduling]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Economic assessment of the Waste-to-energy integrated microgrid system</title><link href="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/waste-to-energy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Economic assessment of the Waste-to-energy integrated microgrid system"/><published>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/waste-to-energy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/waste-to-energy/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="foundation">Foundation</h2> <p>As the global demand for clean and reliable energy surges, developing countries continue to face unique challenges: rising consumption, unstable grids, and mounting waste generation. Traditional fossil-fuel solutions are no longer viable—economically or environmentally. This is where hybrid microgrids powered by renewables and waste-to-energy (WtE) technologies offer a transformative opportunity.</p> <p>Our newly published research, “Cost-Effective Optimal Integration of Renewable Energy and Waste-to-Energy Technologies,” presents a cutting-edge optimization framework designed to build cleaner, cheaper, and more reliable microgrids for regions with limited energy access.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="why-we-conducted-this-study">Why We Conducted This Study</h2> <p>Bangladesh, like many developing nations, faces three major hurdles:</p> <ul> <li>Growing electricity demand</li> <li>Dependence on fossil fuels</li> <li>Increasing municipal solid waste</li> </ul> <p>Remote communities such as Halishahar in Chattogram often rely on expensive diesel generators or unstable grid connections. At the same time, the area generates hundreds of tons of waste daily—an untapped energy resource.</p> <p>Our goal was to design a practical, real-world solution that:</p> <ul> <li>Minimizes energy cost</li> <li>Reduces carbon emissions</li> <li>Utilizes local renewable and waste resources</li> <li>Ensures a continuous electricity supply</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="proposed-solution">Proposed Solution</h2> <p>Our proposed microgrid combines five energy technologies:</p> <ul> <li>Solar PV 🌞</li> <li>Wind Turbines 🌬</li> <li>Waste-to-Energy (FastOx Gasification) ♻️</li> <li>Battery Energy Storage 🔋</li> <li>Diesel Generator (backup only) ⚙️</li> </ul> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/islam2025cost-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/islam2025cost-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/islam2025cost-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/islam2025cost.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> System Diagram. </div> <p>To find the most cost-effective configuration, we applied two advanced optimization algorithms:</p> <ul> <li>Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO)</li> <li>Grey Wolf Optimization (GWO)</li> <li>We also benchmarked results using HOMER, the industry-standard microgrid design software.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2> <h3 id="1-wte-dramatically-lowers-energy-cost">1. WtE Dramatically Lowers Energy Cost</h3> <p>Integrating WtE reduced the system’s Levelized Cost of Energy (LCoE): − 22.6% compared to systems without WtE − 52.8% compared to HOMER’s baseline</p> <h3 id="2-gwo-produced-the-best-overall-performance">2. GWO Produced the Best Overall Performance</h3> <p>LCoE Results: 🟢 GWO: $0.221/kWh 🔵 PSO: $0.223/kWh 🔴 HOMER: $0.468/kWh GWO achieved the optimum 10× faster than PSO.</p> <h3 id="3-pso-achieved-the-lowest-carbon-emissions">3. PSO Achieved the Lowest Carbon Emissions</h3> <p>PSO reduced annual CO₂ emissions to 27,177 tons, outperforming both GWO and HOMER.</p> <h3 id="4-solar--wte--most-reliable-combination">4. Solar + WtE = Most Reliable Combination</h3> <p>Annual energy contributions:</p> <ul> <li>Solar: ~70,000+ MWh</li> <li>WtE: ~63,000 MWh</li> <li>Wind: Lower (location dependent)</li> </ul> <h3 id="5-real-world-case-study-halishahar">5. Real-World Case Study: Halishahar</h3> <p>Using NASA meteorological data, PGCB load data, and local waste profiles, our microgrid met:</p> <ul> <li>107,150 MWh annual demand reliably</li> <li>With renewable-driven generation</li> </ul> <h3 id="environmental-impact">Environmental Impact</h3> <p>Annual CO₂ emissions:</p> <ul> <li>PSO: 27,177 tons</li> <li>GWO: 33,702 tons</li> <li>HOMER baseline: 35,693 tons Both optimized systems show major emission reductions.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="why-this-study-matters">Why This Study Matters</h2> <p>This research provides a scalable blueprint for solving the dual challenges of energy scarcity and waste management.</p> <p>It can benefit:</p> <ul> <li>Remote islands</li> <li>Off-grid rural communities</li> <li>Urban areas with high waste production</li> <li>Disaster-prone regions needing resilient energy It demonstrates that waste is not a burden—it’s a resource.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2> <p>Our work shows that WtE-integrated renewable microgrids can deliver stable, low-cost, and environmentally friendly electricity—especially in developing regions.</p> <p>The combination of optimization algorithms (GWO &amp; PSO) and real-world data provides a dependable framework for future microgrid planning.</p> <hr/> <p>Interested in the full paper? Check out the original research here (<a href="https://ietresearch.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1049/tje2.70148">link to the paper</a>).</p>]]></content><author><name>Arafat Ibne Ikram</name></author><category term="SmartHome,"/><category term="Optimization,"/><category term="LoadScheduling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A New Pathway for Affordable Clean Energy in Developing Regions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Youtube - ReVanced</title><link href="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/youtube-revanced/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Youtube - ReVanced"/><published>2024-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/youtube-revanced</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://arafatikram.github.io/blog/2024/youtube-revanced/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="installation">Installation</h2> <ol> <li>Download and log in to <a href="https://github.com/ReVanced/GmsCore/releases/latest">GmsCore</a> / <a href="https://github.com/WSTxda/MicroG-RE">MicroG-RE</a>.</li> <li>Install the latest version of <a href="https://github.com/MentalBlank/YouTube-Revanced/releases/latest">Build APK</a>.</li> <li>Use <a href="https://github.com/ImranR98/Obtainium">Obtainium</a> to download and install build updates.</li> </ol> <h2 id="patches">Patches</h2> <ul> <li>Options to remove general ads.</li> <li>Option to remove ads in the video player.</li> <li>Option to replace the search icon with a wide search bar; hide the YouTube logo when active.</li> <li>Option to change the opacity of the video player background when player controls are visible.</li> <li>Remove the dark background surrounding the video player controls.</li> <li>Options to enable and configure SponsorBlock to skip undesired video segments like sponsored content.</li> <li>Option to disable captions from being automatically enabled.</li> <li>Option to disable the Shorts player from resuming on app startup.</li> <li>Option to show the dislike count of videos using the Return YouTube Dislike API.</li> <li>Option to hide the autoplay button in the video player.</li> <li>Option to hide the previous and next buttons in the video player.</li> <li>Options to hide action buttons (e.g., Download button) under videos.</li> <li>Option to hide the cast button in the video player.</li> <li>Options to hide and change navigation buttons (e.g., Shorts button).</li> <li>Option to hide the captions button in the video player.</li> <li>Options to change the in-app minimized player</li> <li>Option to disable panels (e.g., live chat) from opening automatically.</li> <li>Option to set which page the app opens in instead of the homepage.</li> <li>Option to trick YouTube into thinking you are running an older version of the app.</li> <li>Options to hide menu items that appear when pressing the gear icon in the video player.</li> <li>Option to hide info cards that creators add to the video player.</li> <li>Option to disable rolling number animations of video view count, user likes, and upload time.</li> <li>Options to hide components related to YouTube Shorts.</li> <li>Options to hide general layout components.</li> <li>Option to hide album cards below artist descriptions.</li> <li>Option to hide the crowdfunding box between the player and the video description.</li> <li>Option to disable the suggested video end screen at the end of videos.</li> <li>Option to hide the floating microphone button when searching.</li> <li>Option to hide suggested video cards at the end of videos.</li> <li>Option to disable the ambient mode when in fullscreen.</li> <li>Option to hide the seek bar.</li> <li>Option to hide the timestamp in the bottom left of the video player.</li> <li>Options to hide components related to comments.</li> <li>Options to hide the category bar at the top of video feeds.</li> <li>Option to enable tablet layout.</li> <li>Option to restore old seekbar thumbnails that appear above the seekbar while seeking.</li> <li>Option to use a different host for user avatar and channel images to fix missing images blocked in some countries.</li> <li>Options to replace video thumbnails using the DeArrow API or image captures from the video.</li> <li>Options for theming and applying a custom background theme (default dark background theme is amoled black).</li> <li>Support to download videos with an external downloader app using the in-app download button or video player action button.</li> <li>Options to display buttons in the video player to copy video URLs.</li> <li>Option to remove the dialog that appears for age-restricted videos by accepting it automatically.</li> <li>Options to enable and configure volume and brightness swipe controls.</li> <li>Option to enable slide to seek instead of playing at 2x speed when pressing and holding in the video player.</li> <li>Option to enable tap-to-seek on the seekbar of the video player.</li> <li>Option to disable precise seeking when swiping up on the seekbar.</li> <li>Option to always repeat videos when they end.</li> <li>Remove restrictions on background playback, including playing kids videos in the background.</li> <li>Option to bypass URL redirects and open the original URL directly.</li> <li>Option to always open links in your browser instead of the in-app browser.</li> <li>Option to spoof device dimensions to unlock higher video qualities.</li> <li>Allows patched Google apps to run without root and under a different package name by using GmsCore instead of Google Play Services.</li> <li>Spoof the client to allow video playback.</li> <li>Check if the device DNS server is preventing user watch history from being saved.</li> <li>Option to remove the tracking info from links you share.</li> <li>Option to disable haptics when zooming.</li> <li>Options for debugging.</li> <li>Option to restore the old video quality menu with specific video resolution options.</li> <li>Options to customize available playback speeds, remember the last playback speed selected, and show a speed dialog button to the video player.</li> <li>Option to remember the last video quality selected.</li> </ul> <h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2> <p>This patch modifies the original APK, and may violate the app provider’s terms of service. Use at your own risk.</p> <h2 id="download-builds">Download Builds</h2> <p><a href="https://github.com/mentalblank/YouTube-Revanced/releases/tag/47">Download</a></p> <h2 id="thanks-to">Thanks To:</h2> <p><a href="https://github.com/j-hc">j-hc</a> &amp; <a href="https://github.com/ReVanced">ReVanced</a></p> <hr/> <p>Interested in the project? Check out the original here (<a href="https://github.com/mentalblank/YouTube-Revanced">link to the project</a>).</p>]]></content><author><name>Arafat Ibne Ikram</name></author><category term="Youtube,"/><category term="ReVanced,"/><category term="AdBlock"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ReVanced YouTube is a modification of the Android YT client that offers SponsorBlock, RYD, Background Playback and an ads-free watching experience.]]></summary></entry></feed>